Taewan Kim PhD Candidate

Department of Industrial Design, KAIST Bldg. N25, 291 Daehak-ro, Yuseong-gu, Daejeon 34141, Republic of Korea taewan@kaist.ac.kr | https://taewankim.io

Research Interests

As a researcher in **Human-Computer Interaction (HCI)** with a design background, I delve into **Human-Centered AI Interaction design**, rooted in a profound understanding of people. Specifically, my work centers on designing AI systems that bolster people's **mental well-being**. I am proud to have showcased my work at esteemed HCI conferences such as ACM **CHI**, **CSCW**, and **DIS**. Recently, I examined the potential of prediction algorithms and their explainability in facilitating self-reflection for mental well-being (Accepted to the CHI 2022). Currently, I am exploring the role of **generative AI** (e.g., LLM) in promoting reflective behaviors among individuals to support mental well-being.

Based on my strength in **mixed-method research** and **human-centered design**, I create artifacts, methodologies, and frameworks. My goal is to inspire meaningful and positive algorithmic experiences for HCI researchers and practitioners.

Keywords: Human-computer Interaction, User Experience Research, Human-centered Design, Human-Al interaction, Mental Well-being, Mental health, VR/AR, Autism, Social Computing,

Education

Sep. 2021 - Feb. 2024 KAIST, Department of Industrial Design

(Expected) Ph.D. student

Adviser: Prof. Hwajung Hong

Sep. 2018 - Aug. 2021 Seoul National University, Interdisciplinary Program in Cognitive Science

Ph.D. Candidate (Transferred to KAIST due to adviser's move)

Adviser: Prof. Hwajung Hong

Mar. 2016 - Feb. 2018 Ulsan National Institute of Science and Technology, School of Creative Design Engineering

M.E. in Creative Design Engineering

Dissertation: Helping Friends Suffering Mental Health Issues: Challenges and Opportunities for Social

support on Social Media from the Peer's Point of View

Adviser: Prof. Hwajung Hong

Mar. 2011 - Feb. 2016 Handong University, School of Contents Convergence Design

B.S. in Product Design

Work Experience

Jan. 2023 - Jul. 2023 Research Intern at NAVER AI Lab (with Dr. Young-Ho Kim)

Harnessing Large Language Model(LLM) in Real-world Clinical Settings: The Design, Deployment, and

Discoveries of the MindfulDiary for Psychiatric Patients' Journaling

Publications

Conference papers /

Journal articles

Taewan Kim, Haesoo Kim, Hayeon Lee, Hwarang Goh, Shakhboz Abdigapporov, Mingon Jeong, Hyunsung Cho, Kyungsik Han, Youngtae Noh, Sung-Ju Lee and Hwajung Hong. "Prediction for Retrospection: Integrating Algorithmic Stress Prediction into Personal Informatics Systems for College Students' Mental Health" *Proceedings of the 2022 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*. 2022. (PDF)

Mintra Ruensuk, <u>Taewan Kim</u>, Hwajung Hong, and Ian Oakley. "Sad or just jealous? Using Experience Sampling to Understand and Detect Negative Affective Experiences on Instagram" *Proceedings of the* 2022 **CHI Conference** on Human Factors in Computing Systems. 2022. (PDF)

Jennifer G. Kim, <u>Taewan Kim</u>, Sungin Kim, Soyeon Jang, Stephanie Lee, Heejung Yoo, Kyungsik Han, and Hwajung Hong. "The Workplace Playbook VR: Exploring the Design Space of Virtual Reality to Foster Understanding and Support of Autistic People in the Workplace" *Proceedings of the Proc. ACM Hum.-Comput. Interact.* **CSCW** 2022. (PDF)

Bogoan Kim, Dayoung Jeong, Mingon Jeong, Taehyung Noh, Sung-In Kim, <u>Taewan Kim</u>, So-youn Jang, Hee Jeong Yoo, Jennifer G Kim, Hwajung Hong, and Kyungsik Han. "VISTA: Understanding Characteristics of Autistic People through a VR-based Interactive Social Skills Training System" *Proceedings of the ACM VRST 2022*. (PDF)

<u>Taewan Kim</u>, and Hwajung Hong. "Understanding University Students' Experiences, Perceptions, and Attitudes Toward Peers Displaying Mental Health-related Problems on Social Network Sites: Online Survey and Interview Study," *Journal of Medical Internet Research - Mental Health* 2021. (PDF)

<u>Taewan Kim</u>, Mintra Ruensuk, and Hwajung Hong. "In Helping a Vulnerable Bot, You Help Yourself: Designing a Social Bot as a Care-Receiver to Promote Mental Health and Reduce Stigma." *Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*. 2020. (PDF)

<u>Taewan Kim</u>, James A. Self, and Hwajung Hong. "Design Constraints and Their Influence upon Design Outcome." *Archives of Design Research* 31.4 2018: 23-41. (PDF)

Poster / Workshop

Taewan Kim, Donghoon Shin, Young-Ho Kim, and Hwajung Hong. "DiaryMate: Exploring the Roles of Large Language Models in Facilitating Al-mediated Journaling" **ACM CHI2023 Workshop** on Intelligent and Interactive Writing Assistants(In2Writing). 2023 (PDF)

Youjin Hwang, <u>Taewan Kim</u>, Junhan Kim, Joonhwan Lee, and Hwajung Hong. "Leveraging challenges of an algorithm-based symptom checker on user trust through explainable Al" *ACM CHi2021 Workshop* on Realizing Al in Healthcare: Challenges Appearing in the Wild. 2021 (PDF)

Taewan Kim, Youjin Hwang, Junhan Kim, Joonhwan Lee, and Hwajung Hong. "질병의 자가 진단을 위한 알고리즘 기반 증상 확인 애플리케이션의 사용자 경험에 관한 탐색적 연구 (An exploratory study on the algorithm user experience of a symptom checker application for self-diagnosis" *The Proceedings of HCI KOREA* 2021. (PDF)

Taewan Kim, and Hwajung Hong. "Studying Students Experiencing Mental Health Problems" **ACM CSCW 2018 Workshop** on Conducting Research with Stigmatized Populations. 2018 (PDF)

<u>Taewan Kim</u>, Young-Woo Park, and Hwajung Hong. "Calm Station: An Interactive Perpetual Desk Object that Reduces Digital Distractions." *Proceedings of the 2017 ACM Conference Companion Publication on Designing Interactive Systems (DIS)*. 2017. (PDF, Video)

Mingu Kang, <u>Taewan Kim</u>, Youngjae Kim, and Junghwan Ahn. "FamCom: A Communication Service Enhancing Conversation Quality Between Elders Residing in Care Hospital and Their Family Member." *Proceedings of the 33rd Annual ACM Conference Extended Abstracts on Human Factors in Computing Systems* (CHI). 2015. (PDF, Video)

Research Project

Apr. 2023 - current

Research Assistant | LG Al Research

Title: Development of Human-LLM Interaction Design for Expert Knowledge Questions and Answering for Domain Experts

- <u>Designed a QA system</u> tailored for academic professionals involved in AI research, addressing user intentions and challenges and providing interaction solutions.
- **Implemented a web-based prototype** of the interaction that aids Al-related tasks and assessed its usability.
- Conducted evaluations to measure the efficiency of the system.
- Explored strategies to extend the system's reach <u>for expert users across various</u> <u>disciplines</u>.

Jan. 2023 - Sep.2023

Research Intern | NAVER AI LAB

Title: Harnessing Large Language Model(LLM) in Real-world Clinical Settings: The Design, Deployment, and Discoveries of the MindfulDiary for Psychiatric Patients' Journaling

- <u>Developed an interactive mental health care system</u> utilizing a <u>Large Language Model</u> (<u>LLM</u>) to generate prompts for daily reflection in individuals with depression.
- Designed a <u>field deployment study</u> to evaluate the system's effectiveness and potential impact on mental health improvement.
- Collaborated with a multidisciplinary team to ensure the system's appropriateness for deployment in clinical settings, taking into account <u>ethical considerations</u> and user privacy.

June. 2020 - Feb. 2023

Research Assistant | Grant Agency: National Research Foundation of Korea

Title: Development and Evaluation of an Adaptive Virtual Reality System to Enhance the Job-Related Social Skills of Adults with Developmental Disorders

- Participated as a <u>remote visiting researcher at Georgia Tech</u> due to the COVID-19 pandemic
- Designed an immersive and adaptive <u>Virtual Reality (VR) program</u> tailored to the needs of users on the <u>autism spectrum</u>, focusing on enhancing their social and job-related skills.
- Developed sensor <u>data-driven feedback models</u> to provide personalized, real-time guidance and support during VR training scenarios, fostering continuous improvement and engagement.
- Collaborated with a multidisciplinary team of researchers, clinicians, and educators to
 ensure the system's effectiveness and usability while adhering to best practices for working
 with individuals with developmental disorders.

Nov. 2017 - Dec. 2020

Research Assistant | Grant Agency: National Research Foundation of Korea

Title: Developing fundamental techniques and design guidelines of persuasive interaction in a positive computing platform

- <u>Designed a positive computing system</u> aimed at enhancing <u>mental health</u> and <u>productivity</u> through persuasive interaction techniques.
- Developed <u>experimental design strategies</u> and <u>implementation guidelines</u> to assess the effectiveness of persuasive interaction design services within the positive computing platform.

Mar. 2018 - Nov. 2020

Research Assistant | Grant Agency: National Research Foundation of Korea Title: Toward Developing a Human-Centered Mental Healthcare Platform

- Conducted **in-depth research on peer support interactions** in social media to identify opportunities for enhancing mental healthcare systems.
- Leveraged findings to design a mental healthcare system <u>utilizing a social media bot</u>, which facilitates user engagement and support.
- Collaborated with a multidisciplinary team to ensure the developed system was <u>human-centered, ethical</u>, and aligned with the needs of diverse user groups.

Teaching Experience

Sep. 2022 - Dec. 2022	Undergraduate Teaching Assistant KAIST CS492(36.492): Smart Health: Data-Driven Service Design for Health and Wellbeing
Sep. 2019 - Dec. 2019	Undergraduate Teaching Assistant Seoul National University 2114.409 Creative Research Practice
Apr. 2018 - Mar. 2019	Assistant Researcher Institute of Communication Research, Seoul National University

Awards

2015	Student Design Competition, Top4 ACM CHI 2015
2015	$\textbf{UNIST Creative Design and Engineering Competition, Silver} \mid \textbf{UNIST}$
2014	Undergraduate Research Competition, Second Place Handong Univ.
2014	Samsung Tomorrow Solution Award, Excellence award SAMSUNG

Skills

Mixed Method User Research

Interview, Survey, Field deployment study, Contextual Inquiry, Grounded theory, Thematic analysis, Statistics (SPSS, R, Prism)

Programming

Python, JavaScript, React, React Native, SwiftUI, HTML & CSS Prompt engineering (for LLM)

UX/UI Design, Fabrication

2D graphic and interface design: Adobe Illustrator, Photoshop, Premiere, Sketch, Figma 3D modeling and fabrication: SIEMENS NX, Rhino, AutoCAD, 3D Printing, Laser cutting, Arduino

Patents

Smart phone data-based intelligent stress prediction and management method US and Korean patent application

Cardiopulmonary Resuscitation Plate for a First-aid Treatment

Korea Patent No. 10-1628073

AR simulator

Korea Design Protection No. 30-0938066

Academic Societies and Services

Peer Reviewing

ACM CHI 2023, 2024 Paper ACM TEI 2018 Paper Archives of Design Research (ADR) 2022, 2023 Paper IASDR 2021 Paper